This is Concorde, flying over Africa on a
flight like no other.
The sun, which was directly above Concorde,
just went completely dark in what was to become
the most unique solar eclipse ever
witnessed.
Total solar eclipses are rare and
typically only last for a few minutes,
but in 1973 scientists
were able to cheat and experience 74
minutes in the moon's shadow by flying in
the only
vehicle capable of chasing an eclipse.
This was an incredible mission that
required pinpoint accuracy and timing to
intercept
the moon's shadow as it traveled at over
2,000 km/h across the Earth's surface.
We modeled the entire thing to show you
what this incredible mission looked like
and how
a small team of scientists managed to
pull it off.
In 1972, French astrophysicist Pierre Léna
began preparing for the upcoming eclipse.
This was to be one of the longest in
history, with a duration of over 7
minutes.
An eclipse this long wouldn't happen for
another 200 years, so he was eager to
make the most
of it.
He was particularly interested in
observing the sun's corona, the area of
hot gas where
the temperatures shoot from 5,000 degrees
to over 1 million degrees.
The corona is usually invisible from
Earth, but during an eclipse, the sun
disappears
and the corona lights up.
But even during an eclipse, studying the
corona is difficult since clouds and the
Earth's
atmosphere get in the way.
And so for the 1973 eclipse, Pierre
wanted to step things up a notch.
And so, Pierre asked legendary Concorde
test pilot André Turcat if he could use
Concorde
to chase down the eclipse and fill the
plane with science equipment.
Aérospatiale, the French side of Concorde,
were excited about the idea and let him use
prototype 001 for the flight, with Turcat
piloting the aircraft.
Although there were faster planes around,
none of them could match the endurance or
cabin space of Concorde.
Pierre and Turcat got to work coming up
with a flight plan that would maximize their
time in the moon's shadow.
Before we look at how the flight worked,
we need to understand the basic
principles of
solar eclipses.
An eclipse happens when the moon passes
in front of our view of the sun, blocking out
its light and casting a large shadow over
Earth.
Most parts of the shadow will only
experience a partial eclipse, but at the
very center
of the shadow is a much smaller area
where the sun is fully blocked.
This is where the total eclipse happens.
As the moon moves, the shadow also moves
across the Earth's surface, meaning that
any point
along the path will only experience a few
minutes of complete darkness.
For the 1973 eclipse, the shadow was set
to begin at the edge of South America and work
its way over to Africa, where the
totality would be at its fullest.
It would be moving over the ground at
around 2,200 km/h, slightly faster than
Concorde's
top speed.
Pierre and his team had to figure out how
to stay in the moon's shadow for as long
as possible before it eventually overtook
them.
But during the planning stages, word got
out about the mission thanks to a data
breach,
something that wouldn't have happened if
they'd used Incogni.
Just kidding, that didn't happen.
But did you know that data brokers buy
and sell our own personal data to
marketing agencies
who add you to a list, usually so they
can send you pointless emails?
The problem is that the information on
their databases can quite easily be
leaked or stolen
by criminals.
Incogni reaches out to these marketing
agencies on your behalf and gets them to
delete any
data they have about you.
They contact each company individually,
so you don't have to.
After a few months of Incogni, my spam
emails have almost completely dropped off.
To protect your personal information and
get rid of spam in your life, visit Incogni.com/primalspace.
And use the code PRIMALSPACE to get 60%
off.
In order to stay in the moon's shadow for
as long as possible, Concorde had to
follow
a very precise flight plan.
The best chance for achieving this was
over Africa, but this didn't give the
team a whole
lot of options for airports.
Most of the runways in Africa were too
short for Concorde, and the hot
conditions meant
that Concorde would have to carry less
fuel during takeoff.
They eventually settled on the island of
Gran Canaria, which had a cooler climate
and a great
runway.
The plan was to take off, fly south and
intercept the moon's shadow at a specific
point over
Mauritania, where it would turn and
follow the shadow across the Sahara
Desert.
But the path of the shadow wasn't
straight, and instead followed a large
curve.
This would make science observations from
inside Concorde very difficult if it had
to constantly
make turns.
And so Pierre and his team came up with a
straight-line path that would touch the
northern
edge of the shadow, cut across to its
southern edge, and end at its northern edge.
This would give them up to 80 minutes in
the shadow without having to make a
single turn.
Since the shadow would be traveling a
little bit faster than Concorde, it would
eventually
outrun it, and so the team had to meet
the shadow at a precise point on the
shadow's
leading edge.
If they were to arrive more than 15
seconds late or a kilometer off, they
would fall out
of the shadow much sooner, and their time
in totality would be drastically reduced.
But arriving at the intercept point so
precisely, with all the variables of
weather, would be
a huge challenge.
Luckily, André Turcat was one of the
best pilots around, and he knew Concorde
better
than anyone.
With a solid flight plan, Pierre
recruited four other teams of scientists
that would
each carry out experiments onboard Concorde.
Since Concorde was going to fly over the
equator, the eclipse would be directly
above the aircraft.
And so holes were cut into the roof of
Concorde, and special windows were
installed to give
the scientists a clear view of the
eclipse.
All of the seats were removed from the
cabin, and the electrical supply was
modified to
provide power to the science instruments.
After weeks of modifications, the fastest
science observatory in the world was ready
to make history.
On the 30th of June, at precisely 10.08
in the morning, Concorde began rolling
down runway
21.
Turcat had decided to take off 20
seconds early, giving him time to correct
for any headwinds
that might slow Concorde down.
This turned out to be a wise choice,
since the weather that morning was more
turbulent,
and they ended up losing 8 seconds during
the climb up to altitude.
With 12 seconds of time still to lose
before reaching the intercept point, Turcat started
deploying small air brakes to carefully
bleed off some speed.
This quickly brought them closer to the
correct arrival time.
But the winds continued to be
unpredictable, and Concorde slowed down
too much, falling
4 seconds behind the scheduled arrival
time, with just a few minutes to go.
In order to make up for this, Turcat
briefly pushed the engines past their
maximum operating
speed of Mach 2.2, and Concorde arrived
at the intercept point just one second
late,
and only a kilometer off course.
At the exact same time, the sun fully
disappeared behind the moon, and Concorde
was now in complete
darkness.
Despite it being midday, the stars became
visible, and the scientists could see the
sun's corona
through their windows.
Concorde was now racing against time, and
the moon itself, and so the scientists got
to work.
Pierre and his team had developed a
telescope that could measure the infrared
light coming
from the sun's corona.
During the 74 minutes in the moon's
shadow, they made measurements that
furthered our understanding
of the zodiacal light, the layer of dust in
our solar system that gets lit up by the
sun.
The team from the US discovered that the
sun's corona has acoustic waves which
cause it to
pulse every 5 minutes.
Concorde flew perfectly for 74 minutes
before it left the moon's shadow and
landed in Chad.
For the scientists and pilots on board,
they got to witness one of the most
beautiful spectacles
from the most unique vantage point.
This remains the longest eclipse
experienced by humans, a record that will
most likely remain
for centuries.
And now for the Primal Space giveaway.
The winner of the previous giveaway is
Bruno.
Congrats!
In the next video, we'll be giving away
this Primal Space-designed Concorde
poster available
in our store.
All you need to do is sign up at the link
below, like the video, and leave a
comment
saying what you think about Concorde and
this eclipse flight.
Thank you very much for watching, and I'll
see you in the next video.